原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/Gk8Ay3QmF6s
原视频发布日期：20200612
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello its Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
After a SpaceX's high profile mission to deliver astronauts to the space station,
在SpaceX公司高调地将宇航员送到空间站的任务之后
they got back to work on their Starlink Network.
他们又开始了星链网络的工作
And the latest Starlink launch was pretty spectacular
而最新的星链发射也相当壮观
primarily because all of the cameras that usually fail during these launches actually worked correctly.
主要是因为通常在这些发射过程中出现故障的那些摄像头都能正常工作
I'm guessing they're working on their communications technology
我猜他们正在研究他们的通信技术
which is a good sign for somebody trying to create a global communications network.
这对试图建立全球通信网络的人来说是个好兆头
First up during the landing on the automatic drone ship, the camera remains stable.
首先是在无人船的降落过程中 摄像头保持稳定
Now this was a night landing at sea and in the distance you'll see there's clouds.
这是在海上的夜间降落 远处有云层
This is the image on the left and as the engines light up you can see those clouds
这是左边的图片 当发动机亮起的时候 你可以看到那些云彩
which were miles and miles away are being illuminated by the flare of this engine which is out of shot.
在几英里之外的地方就被这台在镜头外的发动机的火焰照亮了
This is of course coming down at hundreds of miles an hour
当然 火箭是以每小时几百英里的速度下来的
and basically trying to slaughter an exact stop at the deck by carefully feathering the brakes.
基本上是 仔细使用羽状的尾焰让火箭在碰到甲板的一刻精确地停下来
And yeah, they managed to maintain signal all the way down.
是的 他们一路保持着信号的稳定
Yeah we got a lot of debris on the camera but all we get was the landing.
是的 我们拍到了很多碎片 但我们拍到的都是降落的过程
We get to see the engines being safed
我们可以看到发动机关机
and the last dregs of flammables coming out the bottom.
还有最后一点燃料从底部流出的情形
And it's not quite on center as some of those boosters are
而且这次着陆不像某些着陆一样是完全对准了中心
but it's great to actually see that from a drone ship that the ship that is hundreds of miles out in the Atlantic.
但能从无人船上看到这一切真是太好了 考虑到这艘船在大西洋上 距离陆地几百英里远
But you know by now drone ship landings are kind of old hat.
但你知道现在无人船降落已经是老生常谈了
We've seen them an awful lot
我们已经见识过很多次了
what we haven't seen is an uninterrupted view off the satellite the Starlink satellite deployment sequence.
我们还没有看到星链卫星部署时的连续画面
Now you can see here the upper stage is rotating at kind of pitching downwards from our point of view.
从我们的角度看 你可以看到二级是以向下的角度旋转的
With the way the Starlink satellites deploy is designed to minimize the amount of hardware needed
星链卫星的部署方式是为了将所需设备的数量降至最低
so you have this big stack of satellites are kind of laid on top of each other like a deck of cards.
所以那么一大堆的卫星 就像一副扑克牌一样叠在一起
There's 60 satellites in this stack as the spacecraft begins their slow rotation
有60颗卫星这样堆在一起 当航天器开始缓慢旋转时
that means there's a slight velocity difference
那就意味着有轻微的(线)速度差
and you know centripetal force or centrifugal force depending upon how you want to think about it
也就是向心力或离心力
is gonna want to pull that stack apart.
这样的力会把这么一堆卫星往外拉
So up the side there is this stiffening rod or this rod that holds the satellite in place
所以在侧面有一个加强杆或者说这个杆子可以把卫星固定住
and when that pops out, the satellites now drift free with slightly different velocities,
而当它弹出时 那么卫星就以略微不同的速度自由漂移开来
they will bump into each other a little and they may have to reorient themselves.
他们会互相碰撞一下 也可能要重新定位
There will be a period
这需要时间
where the people on the ground are trying to figure out which satellite is which in the in space
而地面上的人会花时间尝试一一分辨出这些在太空中的卫星
so that they can correctly command them.
这样他们就可以正确地控制卫星
But I mean this is a really beautiful piece of engineering here
但我是指 从工程美学的角度考虑 它是多么地优秀
because it's all about minimizing the amount of mass spent on the deployment system
因为这都是为了最大限度地减少部署系统所花费的质量
so that you can have as many satellites as possible in a stack
这样你就可以在一次分离尽可能多的卫星
and if you're willing to accept that your satellites might bump into each other and handle that
如果你愿意接受你的卫星可能会互相碰撞并能应对这种情况的话
then yes 60 satellites on the spacecraft compared to say OneWeb's much more conventional system
那么 是的 60颗卫星在航天器上 相比之下 OneWeb的系统就要传统得多
which clustered 36 satellites around a core.
它将36颗卫星聚集在一个核心周围
I believe the last two launches they did
我相信他们最后两次发射
they only put 34 satellites on but yeah these are launched at much lower cadence.
他们只放了34颗卫星 但这些卫星的发射节奏要低得多
There would be several minutes between each separation
每次分离之间会有几分钟的时间
to make sure the newly deployed satellites didn't bump into each other.
以确保部署的卫星之间不会相互碰撞
OneWeb的后续详见b23.tv/av456279654
Unfortunately we're probably not gonna see any more launches from OneWeb.
不幸的是 我们可能不会再看到OneWeb的任何发射了
They're essentially bankrupt and the satellites nobody wants to buy them
他们基本上已经破产了 卫星也没有人愿意买了
because they really depend on there being hundreds
因为需要数百颗卫星(才能实现这个计划)
and they are so far from having a complete deployment able to cover the globe
而他们距离能够覆盖全球的完整部署还很遥远
that there's limited uses to which it can be put
而且市场也有限
especially when you consider that anyone looking at this is going to be looking at Starlink as a viable option.
特别是当你考虑到Starlink是竞争对手的时候
Anyway coming back to Starlink, SpaceX released a bit of video which got every space nerd talking
总之回到Starlink SpaceX发布了一段视频 这让每个太空迷都在谈论
because this is a camera inside the fairings watching the deployment
因为这是在整流罩内观察部署情况的摄像头
while the second stage of the Falcon 9 is still firing
此时猎鹰9号的二级仍在点火
and you can see it flying up the middle off to the left but there's a lot to see in this footage.
你可以看到它从中间飞向左边 但在这个镜头里有很多东西可以看
I mean it's obviously amazing to see this point of view.
我是指 这个视角是很惊艳
It's beautiful.
太美了
All the textures in the exhaust are amazing but there's cool information to find here.
排气管里的所有纹理都很惊人 但在这里同样可以找到很酷的信息
Now the first time we actually saw footage from fairings in space was
那么 我们第一次真正看到整流罩在太空中的镜头是
actually because there was some in the Caribbean that was on the beach
其实是因为有人在加勒比海的海滩上
and he found a giant piece of SpaceX fairing
找到了一块巨大的SpaceX整流罩残骸
and on that they've found a GoPro in a special housing.
然后在那上面找到了一个带有特殊罩子的GoPro相机
So he took it out of the housing, sent that off to SpaceX
于是他把它从外壳里拿出来 寄给SpaceX了
and they were able to get the images off the camera.
这样SpaceX才从相机里拿到了图像
youtu.be/4_sLTe6-7SE
And then they published this fantastic video to to youtube.
然后他们在youtube上发布了这段精彩的视频
So you get to see this fairings kind of spinning around in space and falling back to Earth.
所以你可以看到这个整流罩在太空中旋转 然后落回地球上
That I think at the top of the image,
在图片的顶部(的亮斑)
I think that's the upper stage engine firing.
我想那是点火中的二级发动机
It's the brightest thing there except the Sun which is about to come into frame
除了即将进入画面的太阳 它最亮
and I think the Sun is probably brighter than the second stage.
而且我觉得太阳可能比二级更亮
So yeah this is kind of beautiful. It goes on for a couple of minutes
那么 没错 这画面挺美的 视频持续了几分钟
and it's set to the the waltz of the Blue Danube.
而它的背景音乐是蓝色多瑙河圆舞曲
Now this is a much older fairing.
那么 这是一个老得多的整流罩
It's much simpler.
(结构)简单多了
You can see the acoustic tiles on the interior that protect the payload from the sonic environment.
你可以看到铺在内部的隔音砖 这是用于保护有效载荷不受环境声波的影响
There's some ducting that runs up the side from the payload or sorry that the fairing umbilical
有一些管道从整流罩的脐带向上延伸
but you know that's it.
但你知道的 差不多就这些了
Then we have this footage from 2018 from the Paz satellite launch
接着是2018年Paz卫星发射时的这段画面
and the thing to note here I guess is on the left.
要注意的是 我想是在左边
Now there's three your compressed gas bottles here.
这里有三个压缩气体瓶
This is probably gas that's used for the reaction control thrusters
这可能是用于反推力系统(RCS)的气体
because they want to control the descent so they need to get the attitude correct
因为可控的下降需要正确的姿态
so it falls down like a surfboard rather than just flipping around out of control.
这样 整流罩就能像冲浪板一样掉下来 而不是失控翻转
You can also see some rigging for the parachute recovery system
你还可以看到一些降落伞回收系统的装备
and if you look at the payload of course you can see it's sitting on top of the rocket
如果你看一下有效载荷 当然你可以看到它是坐在火箭的顶部
but the engine flares definitely highly overexposed.
但发动机火焰绝对是过曝得很严重了
The next fairing video we have is from the Arabsat-6A launch
下一个整流罩视频是Arabsat-6A的发射的时候拍的
and again of course you get to see the upper stage flyby.
当然 你也能看到二级的飞越
It's a different environment. The Sun is from behind
这是一个不同的环境 太阳从后面照射过来
and the whole thing of course does a complete backflip
而整个事情发生得截然相反
and you see the second stage disappearing off into the distance in the other direction.
你会看到二级消失在另一个方向的远方
Now I want you to again note the acoustic paneling on the interior of this fairing
现在我想让大家再注意一下这个整流罩内部的隔音砖
because this fairing was the first ones to be successfully recovered and reused.
因为这个整流罩是第一批被成功回收和再利用的
Again, this during the separation you have exposure problems but you do get to see the outline
同样 在分离过程中 你会遇到曝光问题 但你确实可以看到轮廓
and get to see that a beautiful image of the second-stage Merlin engine shooting up the middle there.
可以看到二级梅林发动机从画面中间点火的美丽画面
But yeah when they went to reuse this, the acoustic paneling had been removed
但当他们去重新使用这个整流罩的时候 隔音砖已经被拆除了
so this was the second Starlink mission in November 2019.
所以这是2019年11月的第二次Starlink任务的发射画面
Again this is another example of the Starlink satellites
这又是一个例子
being designed for a rougher environment than most satellites.
说明星链卫星在设计上相比大多数其他卫星 能够耐受更恶劣的环境
So yeah they don't need the extra protection that the acoustic shielding offers.
所以是的 他们不需要隔音砖提供的额外保护
And finally in July we had the STP mission on the Falcon Heavy
最后在(2019年)7月 重型猎鹰进行的STP任务的整流罩画面
and look how much space is left in that fairing there.
看那整流罩里还剩多少空间
This was a test mission
这是个测试任务
which meant the fairing was released at much higher velocities and altitudes than the fairings are usually deployed
这意味着整流罩的分离速度和高度远远高于通常情况
so the best part about this video is the fairing performed its re-entry maneuver.
所以这段视频最精彩的部分是整流罩进行了再入机动
And we got to watch the re-entry looking back into the plasma stream.
我们可以看到在再入的过程中 镜头朝向(整流罩运动方向)后面的等离子流的画面
And of course this is an absolutely beautiful video.
当然 这是一个绝对美丽的视频
I wouldn't take to the colors as being accurate because they probably removed the infrared filter
我不认为颜色是准确的 因为他们可能去掉了红外滤镜
but yeah again you know some great images from inside fairings.
但同样也是 一些从整流罩内部拍摄的绝美的画面
So let's look back at the new video and see what we can see.
那么 让我们回头看看最新的视频 看看我们能发现什么
Well obviously there's none of the acoustic paneling here.
很明显 这里没有任何的隔音砖
Over on the left you can see a bright light.
在左边你可以看到一个亮光
That is presumably the light for the camera on the other half of the fairing.
这大概是另一半整流罩上摄像头的灯光
These two fairings are essentially identical
这两个整流罩基本上是一样的
and they lock together to produce the entire fairing that encloses the upper stage payload.
它们锁定在一起 形成整个整流罩 围绕着二级的有效载荷
Up the top you can see one of the pneumatic Pistons which will push the payload halves apart.
在画面顶部 你可以看到其中一个气动活塞 它将把有效载荷的两半推开
SpaceX makes a big thing about using mechanical systems to separate their payloads rather than pyrotechnics
SpaceX大量使用机械系统来分离有效载荷 而不是使用火工品
because they can test the mechanical systems repeatedly.
这样他们就可以反复测试机械系统
In the middle we have these three pressure vessels for compressed gas
在画面中间 是这三个压缩气体的压力容器
and something that's covered by probably a thermal blanket
还有一些可能被保温毯覆盖的东西
which I think that's probably control gear because there's a lot of lines that go in and out of that.
我想那可能是控制装置 因为有很多线路从那里进出
Remember the fairings are practically spaceships of their own,
要知道 (可回收的)整流罩整体实际上是一个飞船
they have to perform this maneuvering in space and then fly themselves back to a position
整流罩必须在太空中进行机动 然后定点飞行
where they can get caught by the ships.
这样(指定区域的)回收船才能进行捕获
If you look at the front here there is a pressurized line and electrical cabling that comes out of the front
在压缩气体瓶前面 伸出一条加压管路和电缆
and then splits up to feed these three three yellowish ports.
然后分裂成三条线路来供应这三个黄色的接口
I'm pretty sure that those are reaction control thrusters fed by cold gas.
我很确定那是由冷气驱动的RCS
There's another set of thrusters at the back but we can also see during some of the recovery photos
后面还有另一套推进器 但我们也可以在一些回收照片中看到
such as this one by Jack Baer that the recovery engineers cover up those ports with tape
像这张Jack Beyer拍摄的 负责回收的工程师把这些接口用胶带封上了
to stop any water or debris ingressing into the thrusters
以防止任何水或碎片进入推进器
and so these bundles behind the gas tanks,
那么这些绑在储罐的后面的东西
I think those are the parachutes and if you look,
我觉得是降落伞 如果你再仔细看看
there's actually white lines that run down and there's some kinks in them.
实际上那里有些白色的绳子伸下来 其中有些扭结
I think those are actually the parachute lines
我觉得那些其实是降落伞的绳子
and those will connect to anchor points with some control capability
这线绳索连接的锚点具有一定的控制能力
so that they can actually steer the parachutes and land the fairings where they need to go.
这样就可以真正地操纵降落伞 把整流罩降落到目标地点
Okay so now let this play forwards so watch again.
那么 现在继续向后播放视频 再看一遍
At the top the pneumatic piston as a fairing separate these will push apart.
当整流罩分离时 在顶部的气动活塞 会把整流罩推开
Do you see that?
你看到了吗？
Beautiful and they're still hanging out there.
很好 它们还在外面
And I just want to pause it here
我想在这里暂停一下
because you can see the limb of the Earth reflected in the edge of that Starlink stack.
因为你可以看到星链堆的边缘反射着地球的边缘
Isn't that beautiful?
是不是很美？
Now the plume behind it,
现在看看后面的羽状物
I'm not clear just how much of this was illumination from the Sun and how much is illumination from the engine.
我不清楚这其中有多少是来自太阳的照射 多少是来自发动机的照射
They had launched about an hour after dark.
这次发射发生在天黑后一小时
And at some point it probably flew into sunlight but some of this illumination might come from the engine.
在某些时候 它可能飞到了阳光下 但其中一些照明可能来自发动机
I'd have to actually do a bit more math on it.
我还得再实际计算一下
Either way it's beautiful.
不管怎样 它都很美
I also wanted to draw your attention to this cylindrical shaped object at the back.
我还想提请大家注意后面这个圆柱形的物体
I think this is part of the parachute deployment system.
我想这是降落伞部署系统的一部分
This is a drogue chute mortar.
这是一个降落伞弹出设备
So since we're inside of fairing, it's protecting everything behind it from air flow
因为整流罩挡住了气流 所以能保护内侧的设备不受气流影响
so if you have a parachute that has to deploy from here,
因此降落伞只能放在整流罩的内侧
it has to be thrown out beyond the range at which the fairing is messing up the air flow.
它必须在整流罩扰乱气流的区域之外被抛出
So that will fire it back. It'll catch the airflow and then it'll pull the rest of the parachute out
这样 降落伞就往运动的反方向发射 抓住气流 然后把其余部分拉出来
and then of course it'll deploy like a wing.
然后当然就像机翼一样展开
So we fall down next to it and you can catch a glimpse off the engine there blowing out that exhaust.
现在 整流罩掉落在二级附近 你可以瞥见发动机喷出的废气
If you look at the bottom of the fairing straight down, you can see the exhaust starts hitting the fairing.
如果你直着看整流罩的底部 能看到废气开始撞击整流罩
So if you look carefully, the rotation of the fairing actually flips around.
那么如果你仔细看 整流罩其实是翻转的
Initially it pitches outwards from the top because we are looking down
起初是从顶部向外翻转的 因为我们是向下看的
and then suddenly when it hits that, the exhaust flips the rotation
然后突然间 废气撞到了整流罩 改变了翻转的方向
and it starts rotating the opposite direction
然后开始反方向旋转
and finally we end up looking down towards the Earth which is still, you know, night.
视频的最后 还是指向了下方的夜间的地球
And I have to play this again because of stuff that I missed.
我必须再放一遍 因为我错过了一些东西
There's a Starlink stack obviously I think that's about you know 14 feet away you know 4 or 5 meters.
这里有一个星链堆栈 很明显 我想那是14英尺远的地方 你知道的 4到5米
So watch the bottom of the fairing looking on the right side. Watch as it wobbles in and out.
所以看下画面右边 整流罩的底部 它在向内外摇摆
Because that's held together mechanically and then given a kick,
因为整流罩的两半是用机械方式固定在一起的 然后在接合处施加力
the whole thing wobbles back and forth initially.
整个东西就开始来回晃动
Again you see the plume hitting it and reversing the rotation there,
再看一次 尾焰的羽流撞击到它 然后整流罩就开始反向旋转
as the fairing starts to point the other way it looks straight back into the exhaust
当整流罩开始指向另一个方向时 它开始直直地往废气运动的方向翻转
and there's a black area there
而且那里有一个黑色的区域
because that is the area of the exhaust. There's being shielded by the payload fairing structure
因为那里(原先)是废气所在的区域 (但是)整流罩把中间这一块的废气挡住了
so it looks like you're looking down into this black hole amongst a bunch of clouds.
所以这就看起来像是一堆云中间的黑洞
And there's just one more photo if you look in this one,
还有一帧视频
you can see that there is an orange glow around the edge there.
你能看到 整流罩的边缘有着橙色的光芒
That is where the exhaust is impinging on the other side of the fairing and it's heating up.
那是废气碰撞着整流罩的另一边 使之发热
Normally when you're at the upper stage, the exhaust expands out so quickly.
通常你在查看二级的画面的时候 废气膨胀得太快了
It cools down and you can't really see it.
一冷却下来你就很难看到它
But when it hits into something, you're gonna see the orange or yellow glow as its, you know, the pressure is enhanced.
但当它撞到什么东西时 你会看到橙色或黄色的光芒 因为它的压力增加了
Now on a completely different note, SpaceX is trying to work with astronomers
那么 话题转到完全不同的方面 SpaceX正在尝试与天文学家合作
to address the various complaints of Starlink satellites being essentially everywhere.
以解决星链卫星基本上无处不在的各种抱怨
The Starlink satellites aren't going to stop launching but they are getting some technical improvements.
星链卫星不会停止发射 但它们正在进行一些技术改进
Darksat didn't work as well as they would like.
黑星的计划并没有像他们想的那样好用
The black paint didn't really reduce the magnitude very much
黑色的油漆并没有真正降低多少来高度
and it resulted in the satellites starting to heat up more than a light.
还导致卫星开始发热 超过一盏灯的温度
Visorsat is their new trick where it's gonna try and shield the satellite.
遮阳板卫星是他们的新把戏 它将尝试罩住卫星
They are gonna adjust the orbit raising manoeuvre to, you know,
他们会调整轨道提升机动 你知道的
try to minimize the reflections from the solar array
尽量减少太阳能电池板的反射
because during orbit raising, their magnitudes are many many times brighter.
因为在轨道提升的过程中 卫星的亮度要高出很多很多倍
And that is just a consequence of being in a lower orbit
而这只是轨道较低的结果
and taking an orientation to work with the solar panels
使用一种降低太阳能板反射的姿态
and allow the engines to fire to push them into the higher orbits.
同时还能让发动机工作 并进入更高的轨道
That being said even at the final orbit, they're probably still gonna be about sixth magnitude
话虽如此 即使在最终轨道上 它们的亮度可能仍然达到大约六等星
and there will be a lot of them.
并且会有很多
And for telescopes such as the V. Rubin Telescope,
而对于像Vera C. Rubin这样的望远镜
they are gonna have Starlink satellites showing up in maybe one in ten frames
星链卫星可能会在十分之一的照片里出现
and they're gonna have to remove those pixels from their data set.
而他们要从数据集中删除这些像素
It's not just the pixels that are eliminated but it's so bright.
这不仅仅是像素的消除 而且(因为)它是如此明亮
It will actually infect.
它实际上会污染
It'll spread to neighboring pixels.
会传播到邻近的像素上
So there will be software required to identify these satellite traces
所以必须要有软件来识别这些卫星的痕迹
and make sure that they don't make it into anyone's astronomical data.
并确保它们不会进入任何人的天文数据中
And this Saturday will also see the first launch of a Starlink Rideshare mission
而本周六也将迎来星链拼车任务的首次发射
where they remove a couple of the Starlink satellites and put on other right share payloads on top.
也就是减少几个星链卫星 然后把拼车载荷放在顶部
In this case they're carrying some imaging satellites for Planet Labs.
在这次的任务中 他们会给行星实验室携带一些成像卫星
So these satellites will go into lower than normal orbits.
那么这些卫星将进入比正常轨道更低的轨道
They'll have to work to raise their orbits.
它们将不得不努力抬升轨道
But they are getting a great deal probably.
但也会得到很大的好处
Most estimates put the cost of launching the 6 satellites between two Starlink launches at 6 million dollars.
据估计 在两次星链发射之间发射6颗卫星的费用为600万美元
For comparison, if they were to do this on a Rocket Lab rocket,
相比之下 如果他们用火箭实验室的火箭来做这件事
they would probably be paying a 30 to 40 million dollars for the same service.
他们可能要为同样的服务支付3000万到4000万美元
And who knows, maybe we'll get some nice images from this launch.
谁知道呢 也许这次发射后 我们会得到一些漂亮的图像
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]